hello and welcome it is September 12th
2023 we're here in the active inference
for the social sciences course at the
Active inference Institute and having a
discussion section on semiotics and
semantics here with
lenaa we're going to be having a fun
discussion I hope if you're watching Ing
live please feel free to write any
questions in the live chat if you
thought about joining and you weren't
sure it's not too late otherwise we're
going to pick up on some key points from
the lecture and on the topic and see
where we go so
Lena welcome back
and however you want to begin let's go
from
there okay hello thank you Daniel um so
let's try to uh recap a little bit where
we left off in during the
lecture um just to remind us where we
were like my point what I was trying to
articulate uh was the idea
of what does it mean to talk about
formal semantics in a way that is not
really
loaded because it's an interesting
thought like to have a
semantic semantics that is actually only
formal right in principle it would
be relative to
[Music]
meaningful uh to meaning right in in the
notion
that active
inference is trying to cash it out
it it is it's more like an idea or a way
of modeling
how how we deal with meaningful
situations and to understand that in a
more interesting more embodied and more
concrete way I was suggesting that we
could use
biosemiotics
as
uh as
a as a model and as a theory
for living creatures like language users
to navigate the realm of
symbols and gave one example which came
from uh James Scott which is the
European forestry that comes with a
practice understanding this scientific
understanding of forests as a
practice that may that allows us
to to refer to
meaningful to meaningful things in the
environment in terms of what is valuable
what's interesting and what is
not
and what and interestingly what what is
more important also from what becomes
available it it is
what is cropped out from the miningful
perspective so things natureal uh parts
of nature becomes left out or understood
as something that is not desirable and
you just
understand what you don't want in
your articulating Principle as weeds or
something that you should get rid
of in respect to what is more desirable
in terms of crops and how you understand
nature in a
more commoditized
way and I find like this example from
Scott kind of very very uh
elucidating uh
in in the book he creates this in the
book he's talking about States how we
articulate life around one specific
notion of state but in this specific
example he has the idea of one official
Observer and this official Observer
establishes a principle of
meaning in a way you have to have a
handle of
Nature and that that also articulates
how Villages and
[Music]
how practices around Agriculture
and and how people relate to each other
within these practices gets
organized specifically for uh one
interesting point that he makes that is
to
appreciate the construction of that is
like a Vision that notices not what
within the meaningful crops but which is
Left Outside the field of
vision and I bring that specifically to
understand
how the principle
can or could be connected to a
generalized
synchronization over time in relation to
those symbols and those practices in
terms of Niche
construction
[Music]
and how those those how this n
construction brings along with the
symbolic use
of uh language uh predictive
value thank you Bren want to bring up
any thoughts on that or any other pieces
or or I'm happy to add a
comment
Bren
okay guess not okay
um a lot to say there there there was a
little bit of a double play with what is
cropped on one hand what is cropped is
the industrial crop that is
being
prepared and um and then the other side
of that coin is what is cropped out and
what what we crop in is the part that
we're paying attention to and we can't
pay attention to everything so it's it's
like two sides of the same coin what we
pay attention to what we include in
attention in our cognitive awareness
leaves the shadow which is what we
exclude and um that could be like the
weeds or the other ecosystem services so
by highlighting the meaning or one
dimension of meaning or one stance on
meaning that only it's like a seesaw
that becomes Salient to the extent that
something else must be deprioritized
so that's how we accentuate these
distributions of meaning and what do we
get from active inference and and free
energy principle beyond for example
what's provided in seeing like a
state I think there's a lot we could say
on that but one piece is we get a
process Theory a real procedural
approach to how different systems come
to do sense making and cognition and
action so just describing the lay of the
land or the history of Forestry in
Europe
or um any other state of affairs in the
world merely describing it may not even
help us determine what's going to happen
a short time later let alone a long time
later or what might happen in a very
different ecology whereas if we
understand the processes of sense making
and decision making that different kinds
of cognitive agents do certainly humans
also though States as cognitive entities
which is what seeing like a state or
thinking like a state entails we get a
process-based
view on what otherwise might be merely
descriptive and along with that
process-based view we gain an increased
ability to make unique explanations
predictions accounts and so
on
yeah we can we we can also we we can
also uh understand
it in a different perspective in terms
of realizing
what becomes sensitized and what becomes
desensitized along the process so you
can you can possibly model that using
this kind of tools and understanding how
that happens over time right I don't
know how how much in terms of
prediction of things that were not
foreseen in these descriptions we can we
can achieve in fact you can achieve some
some level for sure but like that system
should be decide how how that delivers a
very all encompassing prediction in this
kind in this cases I don't believe it
can right I don't think that's the
purpose as well
but we
can at least
have which is might not be as positive
as we want but I think we can understand
how you can gain some understanding in
this process of being more sensitive or
less sensitive to
specific primes and how this
organization organizational principles
uh how powerful they become over
time
yeah I'll read some comments in the chat
and then Lorena or Bren feel free to
just give any thoughts
just upcycle Club wrote hello biomimicry
can enhance biosemiotics by showing us
how nature solves problems and creates
Beauty through signs and codes and by
encouraging us to apply these principles
to our own
Creations
yeah the idea of coding is an
interesting idea but to talk about codes
I don't think we can't that's my take
right I don't understand like you have
we haven't
coded uh any type of principles within
our uh cognitive ability
but uh biologically speaking
however you can understand these
encodings in terms of becoming more or
less sensitive over time to
environmental
cues as the example in terms of uh I is
the example of Forestry right so in that
specific case
this what becomes more what you become
more sensitive and the more you organize
your life or social life is organized
around specific
principles then you can make sense of
these relational
stories uh in instead of just leveraging
one
for
uh difficult to explain notion of
encoding in terms of social cognition
because it will be hard to
explain how the brain will be encoding
these specific symbols but they can be
cashed out in the environment
relationally in terms of those
organizational
principles and then you have this idea
of biom mree like this reiterations and
how that comes along with
but to explain what this mimic or this
meme will be then well it's not so so
straightforward I
think well certainly decompiling the
source code of nature is somewhere
between challenging and misguided or
impossible but that notion of a code
script for biology has animated
discussions of life going back to for
example Schrodinger's what is life he
basically says there's two aspects of
living systems there's their
organizational capacity their
negentropic capacity and then there's
their code script they AP periodic
crystallin informational repository and
then another place that coding comes up
a little bit less in the source code
space is predictive coding and that's in
a way highly compatible with active
inference and gives a deflationary
account on how the semiotics are encoded
rather than saying well this is what
this variable in the source code means
or this is what this codes for or here's
a code switch predictive coding is like
saying we're not even going to touch the
semantics of what the sign is itself
we're just going to hypothesize that the
way that information about the sign is
transferred is through this maximum
information signaling approach called
predictive coding because predictive
coding arose out of video compression
algorithms and only at the end of the 9s
was found to be increasingly relevant
for neural circuitry and so on so it's
another example of where like a
process-based
approach ends up
deflating or
reframing
the
otherwise semantically loaded question
it's like switching out the question of
like where we're going to be with how
we're going to get there and instead of
only focusing on the meaning of the
signs first off as if the meaning of the
signs could be discussed outside of
their
implementation and then even if we could
figure out what the signs were we would
then just turn around and want to know
how they were
transmitted and so predictive coding or
predictive processing in a way short
circuits that or inverts it by first
looking to explain how information is
transmitted that could
support
semiotics and then in the context of
biological systems we naturally have
biosemiotics yeah I I would ask the
question when you talk about information
being transmitted right what that
actually means and I think that's a very
very big topic and a very large
discussion in terms of
um information information Theory when
specifically applying that
into um biological systems I think there
are some interesting people working on
information that makes the case that
Shannon has a point and he's really
interested not in the sem in the
semantics or in the meaning or anything
else it's kind of interest in the
problem of transmission and when you
talk about
transmission
it's worth to ask what is being
transmitted exactly in the terms of of
signals even if you're capturing
specific patterns and you think that the
pattern is the thing that will be
transmitted in that sense but that will
be a
worth
um a worth asking
question to understand like the this
notion of what is actually being
transmit in that sense like information
Pro this information theory is focusing
on this notion of the problem of
transmission and then all the the
concepts that come along to explain that
in terms of uncertainty or noise and
everything that uh impact this
transmissional
processes
and if you're saying like we're
transmitting information in this sense
it is breaking
this semantic code apart yes it is
because like the problem is not focused
on that it's the focusing on the
specific correlations that we have that
we call it we they were mentioning as
information and how these correlations
are are been issue from from the cat go
from what is being picked up in one side
being correlated to what comes into the
other side right how that how do you
lose or gain more information in
that
but the deeper question here
is uh how how can you say that you are
actually gaining or losing that
information because you were defining
this correlation that could be
transmitted or not from the g go if you
don't have that you don't have anything
being actually actually
communicated so with that in mind you
can explain these Concepts in terms of
function and then there's a bunch
of theories that navigate this sense
of uh signaling that is specifically
only functional and then predictive
coding tries
to T tries to push that a little further
maybe but then you have to expl explain
in in a deep sense how this information
is being actually transmitted and
processed and I don't think that is
really really as obvious and as clear as
we think it
is specifically when talking about this
biological way of nature
navigating this proc this
signaling we have to talk about see
because the correlation
if it's def AB in you like from the
beginning you then only have this kind
of transmission for someone specific
that can be able to understand that in
the other side
right well certainly whether we're
talking about a chemical
phermone that requires some type of
receptor or something more ephemeral
like language that requires more of a
semantic reference frame there's
no receiving the message without the
sender it's like they're kind of the two
sides of the phone call um I'll ask a
question from the
chat love evolve wrote how about
cultural encoding and principles in
contrast to
organizational so how do we think
about
cultural
meaning and is and is that similar or
different than
organizational yeah that's that's a good
point right I think if you take very
seriously the example
from the uh the forestry is a
practice
then then I think he has to be
organizational in that sense the meaning
navigates this organizational
practice this organization story
that that
unpacks not
only communication between agents but
also
how how the environment will be
interpreted so and in this sense we will
be transmitted and repeated over time
because it has a history you cannot
ignore like the history of this
practices being pushed further and
replicated through generations right
so the way like the villages will
be organized in terms of that specific
practice for instance can be understood
in a meaningful and cultural way that
organizes
life in virtue
of
some specific principles
that sensitizes our agents towards
specific
directions and I
think I don't know if I don't know if
you get my
point uh for
instance you can talk
about
uh if you think about archaeological
findings and
how uh
archaeological descriptions of specific
Villages and how they navigate uh this
mapping out this this uh these
archaeological
uh sites they usually know exactly if
you have some kind of History already
from this this communities how this how
that City will be likely to be organized
first of like where is the water and if
the water is in certain directions
probably uh there will be certain kinds
of relationships with housing and
communal housings and where they going
to place their dead in relation to this
kind of specific organization principle
the water is here so Plantation will be
not so far away from that and the city
organizes like the village organizes a
little bit in this sense and that builds
up uh cultural practices at least
archaeologically can be explained as
such I I thought of something similar um
organization being the the logistical or
the oper
ational structural aspects so those
would be the roads that connect the
forestry outposts or the circulatory
system that connects the different
organs of
organization and then the culture is a
cause and a consequence of
organization organization is the
enabling conditions for culture to arise
okay so given this road
Network what cultures arise how similar
or different are they convergently what
are their practices or their narratives
that are shared amongst these different
outposts um or in in the bodily example
okay given the organization of the
organs literally the
organizing process or principle then
what biosemiotics can arise with glucose
and insulin and
glucagon and what culturally can arise
maybe even in terms of the generative
model of encultured
Agents as a function of organization and
then what do those encultured agents
do to the extent that they can modify
organization and so these kinds
of
um
unrolling cause and consequence
relationships can be hard to
disentangle because there's not like a
clean single starting
point that can be separated out or
because it unfolds
historically it's not
exactly a reaction in a test
tube so how how does active inference
give us an entry
points into thinking about
this yeah that's one one interesting
thing about active inference that you
you don't really need one uh you don't
really needed An Origin point right you
can start start modeling and start
understanding that at any any given
point and build up from from that story
and see how it unfolds over
time I think that's the most beautiful
idea that you you define your parameters
and then you see from that par
parameters that can be arbitrarily
defined and you can
navate how things change within those
parameters in the generated model right
when you when you have your like
dynamical systems for instance you have
your state space they have some specific
range of defining parameters that
Set uh the limits of that possible
states that you're going to navigate and
if you use this notion
that these two densities brings about in
terms of biiian modeling you can use
this these kinds of tools to understand
how from that specific
parameters
update why what we narrate in active
inference as if belief updating can
change over time in these
terms that's a very nice point it
reminds me of Bruno Lor's actor Network
Theory or ants which kind of Advocates a
similar approach to what you describe
which is like enter anywhere
open-mindedly because in an iterated
modeling or iterated analysis setting
the first proposal or the first Trace
detected we know that's not the whole
picture there may not be a whole or only
picture so we need to answer turn and
iterate and then with active inference
specifically because of the
compositionality that we get within a
layer Collective behavior and then also
the kind of nesting smaller things
inside of bigger
things we can always build something and
then we can go oh wow it's like there's
a lot of top- down influence maybe
there's a higher order factor or slower
factor or a contextual Factor we should
consider
or oh we were abstracting across these
smaller things inside but for a later
day or if relevant we can dive in and so
then it allows a light hold or a grasp
on the proposed generative model
obviously it's map not territory but
even beyond that we always know that we
can expand Lally and across
scales starting from
anywhere in an
iterated modeling process without our
first or even 11th model being proposed
as like the accounts of some complex
cultural phenomena which we're always
going to only ever have our own
perspectives
on yeah I think you don't reallyy that
in so all ENC compassing like you have
one model that will model them all you
can you you can navigate those models in
these More instrumental terms it raises
different questions when you put things
like that in terms of duology of models
and uh models and theories and Sciences
but you they can be also described as
uh tools for describe tools for yeah TOS
for for grasping in
describing
phenomena in a
more non-committal
way uh how much
that how much that Muggles in uh
philosophical or Mor monological
problems it's is still I think under
like debate but it is
still it's still uh it is still to to
bring insights to think about specific
cultural
Collective uh phenomena which is not
it's it's complicated
to because I think what I'm getting at
I'm kind of like going back and forth
but when you talk about social sciences
in modeling usually you have like ways
of model modeling agents or ways of
modeling collectives and active
influences trying
to to come up with a a modeling in which
you can understand agency and
collectives within the same
modeling uh
schema and I think specific specifically
for these cases if you're interested in
understanding uh types of cultural
phenomena among language users
and uh in a specific contexts you can at
least partially understand or have or
gain some insight in this agent
Collective relationship
that that is a little bit more
interesting than we have found so far in
the social sciences because you can have
like or or specific understandings of
memes but then how the agent where is
the agency in that you you lose a little
bit of
agency when you're trying to understand
uh only agents then you don't know how
that kind of scales up because active
influence tries and offers this scale
free uh modeling tools that facilitates
this this
um conversion into agents agents and uh
collectives I would be interested in
asking you actually
how how do you not navigate that when
you talk about social phenomena in ants
or termites
or because then yeah you have very
specific coding demarcations I guess for
for
this uh social
environments yeah it's a great question
it's also
whether it's a uh open wounds or a a
dirty closet that's just shut there's
actually a lot of ambiguity and
unresolved tension around well is the
ant calling social are they social
insects that reifies the nestmate as the
individual and then what they're doing
is like when we hang out and talk so
reifying the nesme as individual makes
the The Colony social but if the colony
is
individual then what nestmates are doing
with each other is not social anymore
than we would describe the liver and the
kidney as having like a social single
cellular interaction but we know that
would be missing the
point and so there definitely is
attention with some of these
evolutionary lineages like ants being
monophyletically obligate usocial all
and only ants are usocial they all live
in the colonies there's no free living
nestmate whereas other parts of the
evolutionary tree there
are life histories that do look a little
bit more like social collaboration that
can then
dissolve and so knowing what level of
lock
in makes something social
when are we socializing and what level
of lockin goes beyond social and it kind
of like makes when the blanket is so
strong around the
social that like for
multicellularity that it it's kind of
losing the social feature again because
if we just use social to mean the
connective tissue or the kind of
lubricant or or the spaces
between everything
then it means
nothing so a real tension is what space
does the Social account
for and is this going to be a concept
with a lot of
creep looking well it's a social
relationship between the roots of the
tree and the fungus and it's a social
relationship amongst the molecules in
the test tube is that too broad of a
social
conception are there
downsides or are there trade-offs
associated with a broader social
concept do we dilute what the social
means and then on the other side C might
we
exclude phenomena that could importantly
be considered
social well that's not social they're
just talking on a train it's like well
that's the other side if we were to have
carving
out encounters that we do want to
include as social and is there a true
social does active inference help us
sidestep or at least negotiate this
territory because we could
develop a generative model or an
ecosystem of shared intelligence with
one person and two Internet of Things
devices and a
bird and a
metronome and just say we made what we
made and then leave it as a second order
interpretation whether that is a social
setting I mean I think you you pointing
at like how the granularity of those
scales right if you have model that one
to one to everything that you already
have it's probably not interesting and
not informative because you cannot like
Define those limits of what you're
trying to
understand and in the other hand when
you do that when you define those limits
if you're too narrow
or you're going to leave out you're
going to idealize also in a way right
and leave out many other parts of of the
system that you're interested
in but if you don't do
that if you
don't if you don't make this this if you
don't make this decision when when
modeling you think then
how how you can have any access
to to the phenomena right and and to
connect this to the forestry so in the
forestry example the um deserada was
Lumber now that may have been a very um
narrowly scoped desire but it's it's a
relevant thing to to want this resource
and then
industrialization science as a process
um
professionalization those allowed the
description and and the handling and
ultimately the kind of top- down um
legibility and control thinking like a
forestry company now with respect to the
social sciences by analogy to forestry
science so now we're entering an era of
increased legibility and control of
social
systems
and human natural capital and attention
as a resource trust as a
resource in a way is being
cropped analogous to produce the content
of lumber but now there are social
content so as the
social goes from being just only simply
the water we swim in not something
that's even compared counterfactually to
Alternative cultural possibilities per
se but
falls under the scope of the
professional management like
forestry then that's when this
discussion of well what's the lumber and
what is the weed that are being
pruned and what ecosystem
Services when we pay attention to
certain parts of Human Social
culture and when we seek
to make more of this kind of
lumber what else does that come along
with and and what
decisions come into
play and that comes along when you see
the
process
or Instagram I don't know Twitter after
what happened to Twitter but
um but yeah the in terms of
attention uh pruning you do have that
very effectively already happening you
already you can see how that happens if
efficiently in the voting elections for
instance it can be very very easily
manipulated and we saw what happened in
elections for instance in Brazil or in
the US
and well all
over
uh you navigate a system of uh attention
organization that selects in
only what he thinks that you're
interested
in in the effect of that in terms of
decision making and in terms of trust in
terms of
um diversity of discourse we have seen
that it can be
devastating the the and the question
would be like how can you make this a
little bit how can you use active
inference and these tools that we
have to make this kind of Technology a
little bit more inclusive without being
super also
disruptive is it even
like a possibility I I really don't know
I think it's an ethical problem that we
have when we talk about social systems
and these principles of attention
exclusion leaving things
out lot to say on that um with modeling
and
interpolating and models whether it's
large language model type or linear
regression
type it is able
to interpolate to put data points within
um an
enclosure of what is already been
described and basian statistics and
other types of prediction algorithms are
not immune to that either if we have
some prior distribution
belief um we believe it's possible for
it to be between 20 and 30°
outside then when we get data inside of
our
bounds we can converge and that actually
tightens our beliefs not always a bad
thing of course and then outside of the
scope of the possible those data are
just seen as noise and they may not even
be integrated so then that can lead to a
reinforcing
process not necessarily an Adaptive One
either where information that's
confirmatory is used to ratchet and
increase precision and then information
that is not
confirmatory is discarded as not
useful it doesn't yeah in this case yeah
it doesn't even enter the uh the
landscape Road of attention of the user
in what I what I'm what I would thinking
in relation to this no this idea of uh
of Forestry is because we
have now organizational principles that
are faster
and more populated with uh information
and attention
grabbing kinds of uh
prompts we transform the
same
[Music]
um we just from the same principle
into
um a harder to
grasp process it's it's hard it becomes
more complex it becomes harder to
describe this the process of
understanding that in terms of Forestry
is kind of way more grounded when you
apply that socially to this kind of
environment that we're talking like
internet or this
highly uh
volatile
um uh and virtual in principle
environment it becomes much harder to
assess what is being pruned out or not
you just don't know it makes it more
clear
that there is a process of pruning you
need to have no control of what is being
taken out you have no idea what's being
like left away from your perspective of
attention so to this topic of intended
or unintended semantic pruning I think
um this has helped me identify attention
if we want to talk about the semantics
or semitics biotics whatever we want to
call it of the letter E in relationship
to letter A we're looking for an
account that might convey
letter but were generalized above enness
or
anus so in some ways we've erased or
abstracted generalized away from the
particulars of the sign's
meaning by taking a Semitic
perspective and so it's like we got into
the game to have semantic account of
biological phenomena or of any phenomena
for biological
entity
yet this
process in a
sense distances us from the particulars
that actually do Grant it that
meaning in the actuality like if we walk
into a Sacred Space and it's like oh
well that is just doing that over there
and this architecture is doing this and
because of the layout people must use
the room this
way that's
removed from the
actual
meaning which is the cause and
consequence with the organization and
culture that we
discussed but that Prima fascia
accounts
doesn't generalize get any
generalization that we make so that we
can talk about multiple places or
multiple letters on a common accounting
framework is going to remove those
particularities so it's a very
challenging Catch 22 whether we want to
really account for the N equals 1 and
maybe even live and act and play and
work in the N equals one versus develop
something that might be satisfying and
cut and dry but it's always going to be
on the sidelines with respect to what it
actually
means but what do you mean like is I
don't understand what you what you're
getting at like is it you mean like is
generalized or not generalized it I
didn't get that like when we have a
general when we generaliz
when when
we ask what words mean what what words
mean Beyond any given word we've lost
touch with what any given word
means but words are what they actually
mean in a
situation so it's just in this
scientific approach to
meaning semiotics and
semantics
we have these
two tensions or a tension to
reconcile between actually giving an
account of the
meaningfulness of the specific
thing versus taking a more scientific
approach which would be gathering a
group of similar
things and finding their shared
attributes which out of necessity must
abstract must crop out
features that are
are empirically or um anecdotally taken
to not matter like we abstract whether
it was a Monday or Tuesday that we did
the
experiments we just combine all of our
replicates together when we do the
scientific
analysis you you
mean you mean if you generalize the
practice you
lose what you being if you generalize it
too much you lose everything that's
meaningful to you in terms of like for
you formalize
it and then you have yeah you have an
empty semantics you have a semantics
with no meaning that can only be
meaningful in terms of how you apply
that in terms of specific practices yeah
it's like I I have a framework for you
know the formal meaning of letters
within words within sentences within par
graphs and then it's like well but now
what's your next n equals one word that
you're actually going to
bring it's not just about building some
abstract
scaffold yeah for bigger and bigger
Boulders of
meaning at some point through our
embodied thought and
action in our experience it is going to
come down into the
particulars and it it doesn't
immediately seem clear that simply
generalizing
[Music]
further brings us
there yeah yeah I particular don't I
don't really believe you can have that
kind of generalization I think
we attempt to build whatever what I see
that's the interesting aspect of the
formal thematics you try to build this
more
General uh understanding that's just
formalizes to model but for that to be
meaningful it has to be embedded in a
way of practicing it like in a
forestry practice you have to be
embedded in a cultural environment in
that can be
actually uh observed in terms of what
happens when a generative model is being
updated or
not is that what you mean because
otherwise I don't really understand how
it becomes
too
yeah it becomes too formal it becomes
too abstract in terms of some I would
not understand what that
is I I'll think of a little more um Bren
or TJ do want to add any thoughts
or
questions
yeah sorry I I think like I don't have a
lot of context I've been like following
some of the discussion but not attended
a lot of these calls I'm like it's all
good
yeah um yeah I don't know uh I think
um yeah I'm in general just sort of
interested in trying to understand the
relationship
between um yeah like sorts of like
constructionist epistemologies and um
yeah like generative models and active
inference um style stuff and um how
active inference style like yeah what
are the philosophical commitments that
active inference involves with respect
to knowledge and epistemology and
there's a sense in which like rational
Choice models often assume a certain
sort of
like um objectivity to beliefs and then
desires are where most the degrees of
freedom lie or something um whereas
there's a lot of like issue like there's
a lot of things that come up once you
start talking about reflexivities where
Concepts themselves become
self-fulfilling prophecies uh what you
believe about what your beliefs about
society and sub shaping the society
itself so there's a sense in which
there's this codependence between the
object of knowledge and knowledge about
that object itself and I I think yeah
like I'm sort of interested Ed in like
how the active entrance ways of thinking
about this offers what perspectives on
those questions and stuff like that um
yeah thank you great
questions yeah so when you talk about
the uh object of knowledge and the
knowledge itself and active
inference
uh
I think you you you can think
of in terms of
this well there's a few way to think
about that I
guess uh the knowledge itself it has to
come epistemically from where your agent
is actually in invaded and situated
specifically in active it's embodied he
kind of needs to have a
model the model is modeling a body is
modeling a body that is in the world and
it's all the time uh situated is never
disconnected to its environment and it's
his and how the history of that
environment right
yeah
uh but if you think if you push that to
the object of that knowledge
uh I don't know how how
different um that
will how different how can you different
differentiate that so sharply when you
talk about active
imprints
because if you think of
uh in terms of a generative model did
what will be
updated comes is updated from a prior
that is always directed in this body in
this
situated uh
realm so they sort of conflate as I see
maybe maybe mistaken but they sort of
conflct in how you going to update your
generative model which it will be at the
same in at the same
time what you know and what you they
object of this
knowledge so I I sorry if I can just
like uh raise a question to that yeah so
I think like I think that there is a
sense in which like with respect to
something that in epistemology would be
called self- knowledge there is there is
a question here that the the active
inference agent has this model of that
is like situated in the body or like in
in its like um like
structure and is also modeling that
structure itself and there is like this
issue of like where
where yeah like the belief is not
unidirectionally dependent on the object
sort of a thing but has this feedback
loop thing comes up there but there's
another way in which I think like uh
where this sort of thing comes where
even if the object is outside of the
body of the knowledge I think that that
that could still come up so for instance
if I live in a if if an active influence
agent lives in a
society of other active influence AG
where currently all of them defect on
prison's dilemma but maybe like on
further reflection they would want to
like again like I don't know what
further reflection would mean in the
active inference sense but I'm like just
saying in the intuitive sense like that
what would it mean for them to like go
from one fix point to another fixed
point where they're all cooperating or
or or something like that and that that
I think is not clear to me like how that
shift can happen in active inference
where it's not just purely using the
empirical information to keep running
the the the mill of the if of your like
free energy equation but also
recognizing the
contingencies and then identif in those
contingencies to make something like
shifts from one state to another like if
if I model that the society is a cruel
space and if everyone models the society
is a cruel space then we will end up
creating a society that is a cruel space
but if only we could recognize that our
belief or our model that Society is a
Cru space is a contingent belief and we
could all somehow negotiate or
communicate and shift to a different
belief about what Society is and Society
is a kind place then we will end up
creating that kind of society or
something
and that sort of like a belief about the
thing that Society is it's not entirely
within the agent like it's sort
of it it it has a weird inter subjective
character so it's not entirely outside
of the agent either but it's not
entirely in like internal to the agent
either or something
yeah
yeah you can think of that like you're
talking about active inference action
comes first right you have to you don't
have the knowledge like inside your head
waiting for you to to push that out of
the action has to come first so if
you if you take that as a principle an
organizing principle it depends on the
contingency of your actions the
possibilities might be limited by your
situated
um condition but they are limited it
doesn't mean that you don't have like a
range of options from that state space
in which you can go you can navigate so
you can navigate it for the good or for
the bad but it starts with the the the
action perception Loop starts with the
action all out a few other pieces on
that TJ very good point like when we see
the pragmatic component of action as
self-fulfilling epistemic component of
action having to do with gaining
knowledge and the salience of
information but the pragmatic component
is about bringing our observations into
alignment with our preferences and then
you identified two related settings one
of them is like pure intra subjectivity
like I expect myself or I find myself or
I habitually think about X well that's
kind of a trivial self-fulfillment
because thinking about something is its
own
fulfillment and then when we're in this
second person or social
space we can agree on little performance
art or on a game and games give evidence
to that that when people are able to
perform communication or message passing
such that that new expectations or
preferences are set whether more top
down like more seeing like a state or
more laterally more like Collective
Behavior then those regimes can be
embodied and then you brought up a very
important point about the awareness of
the contingencies or aware awarenesses
of adjacent posses or of
counterfactuals so the body might be um
we could model its more morphology as
doing some computation but that doesn't
mean that the the morphology has an
awareness or can explore a
counterfactual like bodies are not
always exploring every
counterfactual um because skin is in the
game but again mentally it's very cheap
and easy to consider counterfactuals and
situational awareness of social settings
especially if it can be not understood
but communicated
opens up a space where we're all playing
prisoners dilemma now there's
parameterizations of prisoners
multi-agent prisoners dilemma where
tragically we just all defect all day
and never learn there's also
parameterizations where you just start
all cooperating and never defect and
then the interesting settings are where
there might be like phase
transitions or where a perturbation
moves the system from one attractor into
another
attractor so there's just a lot of
richness
and that's the work of building
generative models in that iterated
modeling
process to to unpack and
refin and active inference isn't going
to have a stance on the prisoners
dilemma we can use active inference to
to describe the prisoners dilemma but
active inference isn't going to come
down on on literally even a little 2 by
two Game Theory Matrix so we can then
extrapolate that active inference is not
going to come down with an
opinion on something
significantly more rich and real than a
2 by two Game Theory
Matrix and so that
work is
what people enact in applying active
inference
right and I think like my question is
something like but in so far as like
humans try to constantly improve their
social
games how can we model that sort of a
prior over your actions or
policies uh that enables that sort of
like Progressive
um um Improvement or something
well you you can we we're assuming that
we're trying to improve right we we we
don't know that but we can model them as
improving but like following Daniel's
lead you we're talking about these
specific games and contingencies they
they they this these transitions from
one state to another specifically if
you're talking about this modeling of
social actors and talking about several
actors if your model involves several of
them will not be really linear right you
don't have like a easy smooth transition
of improvement you can capture over time
as
modeling how they might tend to go
towards a direction and understand that
as Improvement but that
takes specific iterations that will not
be fully linear I guess specifically if
you want to understand error and
Improvement instead instead of try and
error but tryer and adding up into this
eror like error
Improvement but when you're modeling
specifically with dynamical systems for
instance you you you're not going to see
a full linear story and I don't think
you're going to see
that uh if you're modeling using active
inference and multiple agents agents
I'll add one piece there so H how can we
go about modeling multiscale social
goals
so we could think about you know
different citizens in a region
and they the model is going to choose
what knowledge to realize in the
generative model like what you put into
the calculator it's going to calculate
upon now this happens to be a elaborate
stochastic method but if we only tell
people yeah there's just your personal
income optimize for that your preference
is to have that be higher well then the
simulation is going to unfold a certain
way if we say well there's your personal
financial income and then there's your
city and then there's your
region then then that opens up through
through different um mechanisms you know
maybe an
individual goes flat or neutral on the
personal in service of a larger win at a
at a higher level well now what if the
modeler says it's not just about the
financial income now we're also going to
have this secondary Criterion well now
different agents could attend
differently to those two different out
outcome variables
and maybe there's one simulation where
50% only care about this and 50% care
about that and it works perfect or
doesn't
work it's like a broad
surveying you know or Lego set or or
grammar or or active inference
ontology
for scoping very broadly and very
inclusively but
all the work is in the
real simulation
development and
sweeping because very little could be
said
about a game theory game if you didn't
know what the parameters were in The
Matrix you wouldn't know whether this P
prisoners dilemma was going to be like
an always cooperate or which agents with
which strategies would or wouldn't
cooperate if you don't know what the
Matrix looks like so
before the values have kind of been
filled
in it's just like actually describing
the adjacencies and the counterfactuals
and the contingencies of our scientific
model but that's still prior to having
the model in hand and the model you know
so now we're looking at that tree in the
European forest and like well if I had
this tool then I could cut it down this
way if I had this tool I could cut it
down this way or I could wait it's
like
that's alternative actions about that
tree now in the social science
setting discussion of different
scientific methodologies are like
counterfactuals about that social
tree
yeah and specifically if you're
navigating this kind of game theoretical
models if that's what you're interested
in you can even Define in terms of um
prisoners dilemma for instance uh
specific values just see what happens
when everybody def
um deflects and in how frequent and
modulate those frequencies in terms of
specific uh in multiple iterations how
how how you going to uh build up the
wage
or the tendency of deflecting again if
your neighbor deflected once and
deflected twice or three times or uh and
see how that we
accommodate over time how many times
this agent will change its behavior
until it stops changing the
behavior but that you don't
really but that's that that again you
use you might use a ban understanding
Aion model for that but it not
necessarily
[Music]
explain
um it does not necessarily explain the
action fully I mean socially you just
you're modeling only the interest of
that specific
actor I I I have a slightly meta
question if I can ask both of you uh I'm
not sure how these calls usually go uh
I'm curious what are your interests in
active inflence what do you think like
what brings you to active influence and
like what do you think what do you think
active
adds to our theoretical understanding
and in what ways or
something right I go for
it
well I think I was trying to touch upon
that before and how we
can if if if you're navigating for
instance behavior in terms of Game
Theory this kind of modeling if you're
talking about like trust games for
instance you're going to understand how
this to addic interactions evolve over
time specifically over
interactions but you don't have an
account of change because you have very
limited options of
actions
and you don't have an account also own
scales and I think active inference
tries to add a little bit in account of
how you can scale that and how
uh
uh how can I more parameters into the
game and see how they evolve with a a
more
clear um understanding some a richer
understanding that for instance when you
talk about specific interactions in Game
Theory so when you that's one one aspect
that active influence kind of
contributes another point is because we
have
this parameterization
that is specifically in terms of belief
updating and also in terms of
Dynamics we are always talking about uh
agents that will be situated and
embodied and have a very specific
uh synchronization with the environment
all the time because when you talk about
active inference the action comes always
first so you have a less you try to have
a less reductive
model spec and when you want to model uh
cultural agents and Collective action I
think that's kind of desirable that's
what you're looking
for is it also your area of Interest
sorry is it also your area of
Interest mine or is that Lorena's area
of Interest
Lorena's what do you mean
oh sorry like my question was also like
what brings you to active inference and
I think you answered a lot of ways in
which active inference adds theoretical
value but I'm I wasn't sure like if that
was also your subjective interest or
motivation it's my subjective interest
yeah I'm I'm curious to see how that
pans out right I I I'm interested in how
that helps us
to to think of this type of
uh phenomena
and I'm I'm very interested in how this
relationship from Agents to collectives
and Back Again work
like and I think it might give us
some well you give us some very
insightful way of modeling these
relationships and navigating is as you
want because this this uh feature of
being scree is kind of helpful in to
looking things you can you can Define
your uh Mark of blanket in terms of are
you interested right and see what
happens I don't know yeah I'll just give
a few thoughts even though also surely
some of these thoughts are are
scattered um you asked TJ what is active
inference add to our theoretical account
of the social it does many things in in
my view and that's what makes it so
valuable epistemically and pragmatically
it gives us the
expressivity within a scale to describe
Collective behavior and across scales to
describe nested systems so that brings
continuity to discussions of the social
with broader discussions of the the
biological ecological computational
physical and so on so that's a
multiscale transdisciplinary element
active inference provides us with
legible first
principles which can either be taken
instrumentally as just
teristics and also in certain situations
can be viewed
empirically as justifiable first
principles
and then from those legible first
principles which are not English
specific they're already in a
space that has a lot
more possibility and
promise than for example a mere
enumeration of important adjectives or
nouns we can develop lists of important
adjectives and
nouns when we have a broader cognitive
modeling
framework and so this methodological
turn then supports just a tremendous
diversity of thought and
work instead of asking us to kind of go
through the eye of the needle and you
know get on board with this
one ranking of features and then try to
apply it more broadly that's like an
overfit before the cart situation with
actm we can expand the methodological
discussion connect it to theoretical
physics and Mathematics in ways that
really haven't been seen before and then
that opens up more than it closes down
it brings up more questions than it
resolves in and of itself but it opens
the questions that can be resolved like
what generative model can I make that
will keep the temperature in this
building livable but active inference
isn't going to have a stance on what you
should do for that
building so we need to in a way take a
step in the methodological
Direction which I see as moving towards
active inference to
enable a million steps in different
directions I have a bunch of questions
here uh I think one is probably just a
reference question uh there are three
topics that I'll say if you guys have
any papers or articles on those things I
would love to like get a reference one
is in what ways can we model a
collection or an aggregation of active
inference agents as
a like super agent or like super like
active inference super agent or
something and like how how does this
like decomposition and
aggregation uh like flexibility work in
different context like if there's like
work that tries to either
make informal commentary or formal
modeling either ways I would love to see
that
secondly on the first just on the first
check out the previous section of this
course on Collective Behavior where I
reviewed many such works great thanks
okay it is it on the same notion is it
linked from the same notion thing all
all in the same places and in the same
playlist with this course same syllabus
yes got it okay um the second is is
there an active Insurance account
of say markets or economic interaction
wherein like your your prices act as
some sorts of like information signals
and like like can can use active
inference to then talk about aggregation
in of market and enties or something I'm
guessing this would also be covered in
the same list indeed people have
explored cognitive economics and people
are working on it but that doesn't mean
it's a done deal theoretically or
especially in practice so keep going
quite it's quite experimental still but
there are a bunch of people working on
that I
guess I I don't remember any specific
paper right now but I can I can look it
up in uh for to you but yeah yeah it
would be great uh I I can drop my email
address here yeah
sure uh the third is probably more
trickier than both of these which is is
there an active inance account of
natural
language
[Music]
um yes thankfully colleagues like Elliot
Murphy and others have
explored specifically the linguistic
aspects of natural spech Beach I think
Lorena's lecture and area of focus
generalizes a bit beyond
specific natural language because we're
talking about semitics and
semantics in more Intermodal sense
however yes there's been limited work
from uh computational Linguistics and
neurobiology perspective on
speech okay so then
uh okay so you said something like first
principles stuff when you're making a
commentary on what act of inance brings
I have still I have I'm still often like
struggling what is active inance
offering and I like try to encounter
different things I think I enjoy a lot
of philosophical questions that the the
conversation opens up but like I'm still
like very ambivalent about the theory um
and when I read like this new book uh
which friston has not written uh but
like is Anor I don't remember was the
name of the book
um uh I don't yeah I don't exactly
remember there's a book right which is
like supposedly like supposed to be the
Canon and like friston is a co-author
but in the preface he
says so that's the 2022 par friston pulo
textbook right par
yeah yeah I wouldn't quite say it's the
Canon since it's a short book but
certainly it is a landmark moment for
the
fields right and when I read
that the one thing that bothered me
was it brings up the helmos free enery
thing but it's sort of argues it by Fiat
like okay this is a simple principle it
can Model A lot of things
but that doesn't tell me why I should
why I should trust it like what what is
the reason to act why why does this
principle lead to cognition like what
like sure youve posited a very simple
principle and then said hey look this
simple principle can explain so many
things but well it can it also explain
things that don't look like cognition
and like I like I'm not sure like
there's an I I got an account of why
that principle is like uh works or
something right go for it I'll think of
some other ways to say it yeah you you
you can think of like modeling by
construction and modeling by first
principles and if modeling by first
principles you have you have some
limitations in
which you cannot fully explain some
things but the virtue of the model model
and how the first principle organizes
everything that comes along with the
model usually might be sufficient or
might be a useful a useful tool to help
you explain that phenomena that based on
the first principle that you were
bringing
along and that's one way of one part of
answering this question I think it's
might be a big question for the for the
F yeah here here's some short little
threads on
that yeah we can
describe
maladaptive cognitive systems or
adaptive cognitive systems whether
something's adaptive or not is always in
relationship to its Niche like the
foraging algorithm that works in the
desert doesn't necessarily work in the
rainforest so these systems are not like
intrinsically adaptive or not we want to
have natural language that allows
sentences that are valid and invalid
and have different kinds of semantics so
again this is just an expressivity
framework that enables people to build
cognitive models of high reliability or
important settings or you could make
something that looks just like a
beautiful circuit board and not even
worry about what the outcome is so so
yeah for sure you can describe all kinds
of systems that would be like um having
a uh less than functional methodological
system if we said well we're doing a
linear regression framework but we only
want positive regressions it's like well
no at the methodological level we want
it to be able to do any slope so here in
the cognitive modeling setting we want
more expressivity so that we can
actually construct the ones that we're
interested in and then how does
this really do
cognition how is it that a first
principles like surprise minimization or
the bounding of surprise through free
energy how can that really cover so many
cognitive
phenomena that's the question and the
play but how is it that Newton's Laws of
Motion can describe so many objects
being dropped off a
tower how is it that basian mechanics
can describe so many different priors
being
updated and so by understanding
cognitive paths as Paths of least action
which is the free energy
principle a wide variety of
models
become of a of a similar
kind now become available
yeah whether that's useful to a given
person in a given setting like if you
make an active inference model of your
business it doesn't mean you're going to
succeed if you make a self-driving car
with active inference it doesn't mean
it's going to going to work this isn't a
guarantee of
success but it's a method that can be
utilized and we know that the method
reaches different kinds of modeling
outcomes and
supports subsequent perspectives and
models from where it
reaches but we can't a priori limit
where the method reaches to like only
the successful ones or only biological
systems then we wouldn't even have the
expressivity to talk about cognitive
ecosystems with synthetic
intelligences um and when you're talking
about cognition also we can use these
kind of first principles to model
aspects of cognition but you might not
necessarily think that cognition is
encompassing like that everywhere all
the same but you can use that to model
specific things that you're interested
in in cognitive behavior like adaptivity
does it give me any insight to
understand what is adaptive adaptive
behavior for
instance and which kind of insights do I
get are they interesting are they useful
so that's what the Ava availability that
this kind of model bring along so you
can you don't have to believe in in the
whole story but it gives you a lot of
Leverage to ask ask questions and what
kind of questions you'll be
asking h okay so let's say that like
free like active inflence and free
energy allows me to talk about
systems uh
but does it give also give me
vocabulary to then classify those
systems in terms of let's say adaptivity
would be one property but like there
could be other properties in terms of
like how
much how rich the world model is or
stuff like that or yeah um if you have a
portfolio of generative
models you could summarize them
according to the TJ statistic you could
summarize them according to the number
of nodes you could put them into a
common environment or different
environments and summarize their
activity in any number of ways but we
can't talk about a ranking or a
summarization of a portfolio of
generative models that's not in hand
this is a framework that lets us build
those diverse generative
models and then in a very open-ended way
do model comparison model selection
model adequacy all the kinds of complex
systems
engineering
methods that we
want and also I would ask you where do
you see a
peer or a comparison first
principle you know active inference has
legible first principles which are
reflected in the active inference
ontology and expressions using it which
can be represented in natural language
so that's the talking about it but it's
not only represented in natural
language other Frameworks have other
first principles that may or may not be
legible and people may choose different
paths to go down for whichever number of
reasons well right models like they have
the virtue can compare them and see
which one gives you the best Insight
that you're looking
for well so yeah I think like something
that I could compare to active inference
is like say the ban utility maximization
thing and which has a different onology
I'm not a fan of that either like that
also I'll just that basian utility
maximization is a special case of free
energy where there's no epistemic value
all you have is pragmatic value and so a
special diminished necessarily not
necessarily you have value of
information and you have explore exploit
tradeoffs in ban utility maximization as
well like you like like if you load into
your utility function if you can beg the
question and load epistem into pragma
you're right then all you need is pragma
but in expected free energy we have
epistemic and pragmatic value which is
what enables us this expressivity but I
think we're aligned on
that right I I think like I'm somewhat
like also slightly confused because in
the basan utility like between the
languages comparing the languages as
such like in the beijan utility
maximization the exploration parts that
are are prioritize based on your X
an um estimation of on the value of
information uh
whereas I'm not sure that all holds true
for the act of inflence model as well
that the ep the epistemic exploration is
prioritized or valued in terms of
some of the same uh pragmatic thing as
well you yeah you you'll have a a a lot
to explore and learn you can make a mod
that is 8020 or 2080 or 100 Z between
epistemic and pragmatic there's nothing
we can say across generative models
about whether active inference
prioritizes epistem or not because you
can make a model that's
100% or zero so sorry I I meant more
like does active entrance allow us to
talk about systems that the beijan
utility maximization doesn't allow us to
talk about I'm talking particularly
about expressive power of the language
yeah um like is it like are there things
that the bity maximization can talk
about that active inference cannot other
things that act to influence talk about
that b maximization cannot two short
answers one short answer utility
maximization must cram epistemic value
into pragmatic
value we gain more expressivity when we
can articulate out pragmatic value which
is the alignment of preferences with
observations from epistemic value which
which is Information Gain so that's a
huge articulation and the second thing
is when you're in a anything
maximization framework when you're in a
utility function now again begging the
question how you constructed this
function that you're trying to maximize
but when you're in a maximization
framework we have a well-known set of
approaches for finding local and Global
Maxima using optimization or
maximization
Frameworks what active inference
uniquely provides is it describes the
path that that cognitive thing
takes as a path of least action that
minimizes surprise so instead of
climbing to the top of the hill oh are
we on a Foothill or are we on the
biggest hill we're like a ball rolling
to the bottom of the hill finding the
least surprising path now that least
surprising path can still include
novelty and Information
Gain but it turns out to be a lot more
tractable and connected with statistical
physics and quantum mechanics when we
talk about the path of least action ball
rolling down the hill rather than this
sort of question begag on top of a
mountain climbing adventure basian
utility
approach but it's up to each person to
feel how they want to feel yeah and I
think that a little a little bit what's
in the book as well when you take the
low and high road for free energy
principle right because how much you
want to have your utility maximization
function
being uh disconnected to the pragma to
the to the
action because when you're modeling
Behavior it will be hard to do that
independently like you have a lot of you
have way more assumptions you committing
to much to a greater level of
assumptions for your utility function if
you don't do
that because with the pragma with with
the action first that
pragmatize you you you have reasons to
describe have reasons to believe why
that information gain works the way that
it
does you can leverage some explanations
on that with without it you you have you
have you you have a model that has more
assumptions and I think if you have a
model with less assumptions is
always healthy here let's say
so yeah so I think like that that that
does talk about the compare compartive
analysis of the expressivity but I I
would also say as a meta point that like
I'm not happy with either of those
languages I'm like I I'm suspect that
both of those languages claim certain
ontological assumptions and I'm like
always suspicious wait but like where
are these ontological assumptions coming
from a few other points we tap into an
absolutely meaningful Nexus of
statistical methods and message passing
schemes with active inference if you can
State something in the active inference
ontology and construct a generative
model
then message passing algorithms can be
deployed that cont tractably compute
that model so that's absolutely
non-trivial otherwise it's possible just
to get wrapped up in some analytical
formalism but then once you want to do
that on a 4K
video now you're on Square zero with the
computer engineering this is not that
way and then I will respond to your
metap point with a metap point which is
when we've enumerated the
Alternatives the one that we like best
personally I feel happy with I'm also
open to New Alternatives arising but
being unhappy when all things considered
is in play
why what bothers you specifically on the
ontology
of uh the
active yeah like I I I think like I'm
still looking
for I I don't know what exactly I'm
looking for but I feel dissatisfied with
the account given for why Helm's free
energy uh least action thing like
is the central thing here or
something like why does it work like why
does this
principle
yeah there's a lot of funy answers I
could give there yeah that that Delta
that
discrepancy that's curiosity and that's
the space of the open and that's
learning and that's your unique
contribution to make and that's
everything so that's not just a thorn in
your shoe that's like our experience of
action amidst
uncertainty which is the water we're in
and so whether we take a higher order
narrative perspective on that
discrepancy being dissatisfying or that
discrepancy being satisfying I think
it's pretty cool I just need to minimize
my surprise there yeah and you can
choose to minimize your surprise through
your attention you can choose to
minimize surprise at a higher narrative
order like I'm satisfied and complacent
that I don't understand number Theory
but I use numbers to count objects
around me so that discrepancy and
understanding knowing that there's a
thousand years of research that could be
done on
numbers it doesn't unsettle me but for
someone else that might be unsettling
and that might lead them to ruminate it
also might lead to do a PhD and number
Theory so just different paths for
different individuals and
contexts but there's always so many
Technical and meta levels with ACM
huh okay so I don't want to like keep
you guys over time uh but I would ask
one last reference based thing which is
um are there active inference accounts
of see like a state
phenomena uh in any literature I think I
heard you mention it once so I was like
yeah like of
this yeah check out live stream 33
series but also this course that we're
literally actually enacting in with
AVL is where these accounts come to
roost and where we're creating a space
to develop it and it's not a cathedral
for us just to spectate at today but if
you want to make an active inference
generative model of whatever social
setting when you have the model in hand
a lot of your questions will
be
sidestepped okay where is the 33 thing
that you mentioned if you go to the page
with all of our Institute live streams
and look in the live stream series like
the paper discussions in the 33 series
or a zero video with background and
context and then we have a one and A2
conversation with the authors but AVL
who's also the course coordinator for
this course and chyos research like
ail's and and colleagues work has
heavily built on the seeing like a state
thinking like a state optimal grasp all
these different
topics yeah I'm yeah I'm on your YouTube
channel I'm slightly finding it hard to
find the
thing um if you look up live stream
033.0 or if you go to in the video
description of any video where it says
all live streams here go there and
search for but you you'll find it and
you can always email us or get in
contact but yeah and I think of V paper
like thinking like a state also can help
you a lot to understand how how um
active INF modeling is useful for the
social sciences in comparison to other
types of modeling he makes an
comprehensive description
interesting great thanks uh yeah and
this is this is our first iteration on
this course we are going to
continue bringing new information to the
table and supporting individuals who
want to build generative models you know
around this
area whether part of an internship
program or part of a course credit or
different kinds of programs that we'll
be able to
develop but this is the real thing and
we're able to work with people who want
to think and
do makes
sense indeed any closing thoughts on TJ
then I will go and then Lena with the
last
word uh no that this was great thanks
thanks for the
conversation
thank you well thank you for Brandon TJ
for joining Lena for the lecture this
was a fun discussion we never really
know where or how it's going to go but
I'm glad that we could cover so many of
these topics and probably raise more
questions and
footholds than door slams so thank you
againa yeah thank you for inviting me
and I think active
inference like holds a lot of space for
experimenting as well some things you
try to see if they make sense and if
they're going to hold up and open new
questions and that might be an
interesting aspect
of uh of the framework
itself thank you everybody thank you
everybody for the great live chat
comments there's a lot there I couldn't
read it all so till next time
right